so
[Music]
hello everybody good evening and good
day to all of you and welcome to the
latest episode of the ask a budget show
i hope you're doing you're all doing
well
uh let us see who all is there with us i
can see
our gear deep nikhil singh srishti
abhishek soham
diaz
swap nail tejas
[Music]
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you thank you all for
being here
and uh do let me know if my image is all
right once in a while there is an issue
sometimes so
hopefully i'm visible clearly
and i'll keep an eye on the
chat from time to time to see how it is
going
all right so let's get into it i've
picked a bunch of questions we'll do a
few questions maybe 20 or so and then if
there is time i will take a few
questions from the live chat so if you
have any questions keep that ready for
the end all right i can see my images
clear thank you all for letting me know
thank you
all right let's get into the questions
question number one is by akil
the question is uh i'm from mauritius
and recently india has been building an
airstrip in agalega island which belongs
to mauritius the government here did not
reveal any information concerning the
contract and a lot of conspiracy
theories are being made
by the mauritians that the island will
become an indian air base
can you give some useful information
about the contract between india and
mauritius what's the geographic
importance of the agaliga islands
to india
is been india building the air strip for
free okay excellent question so let's
take a look at the map and see where
these islands are
so that we understand the geographical
significance and other
issues where's the map here it is
so we know where india is let's go
southwards in the indian ocean
so here we have the twin islands of
mauritius in reno
the india belongs to france now the
agalega islands are really far away from
mauritius it's about a thousand
kilometers north
and the capital city of the agalega is
onesec
this here
so these two islands are the island
islands in question where india is
building some sort of military or naval
facility as you can see it's really
really far from mauritius the distance
may be more than a thousand kilometers
let me find out the distance
if i measure the distance from here all
the way to
il maurice it is
yeah thousand plus kilometers
so
that's the situation it's actually
closer to the seychelles
the agaliga islands now
let's take a look at what this place
looks like i mean uh
the population of this
these twin islands is i think less than
300 just a bunch of people who live
there
and this is what it looks like and as we
can see there is an airstrip over here
and uh
there are a couple of little settlements
the capital city so to say is one sunk
this thing here
there is a shiv mandir here and various
other things
and this is the airstrip in question i'm
not sure how recent this image is but
as we can see it's a functional airstrip
and there's a secondary smaller airstrip
as well over here
doesn't seem to be a lot of development
beyond that but yeah it's an airstrip
and
possibly something else going on there
so that is the uh
geography and the
what's going on in this place it's very
far from mauritius but it belongs to
mauritius for sure
so the question
is
okay so why is there a controversy or
controversy or an issue so uh recently
there were a couple of articles one in i
believe al-jazeera which is an arabic
mouthpiece and the other one i think was
from some australian publication which
is a us mouthpiece
and well the arabic world is controlled
by the us more or less so uh they have
raised the question of
what is india doing in agalega what is
the relationship like what is the
contract like
what exactly is
happening and they have claimed
that the people of these islands these
less than 300 people are upset about
what's happening there
yeah that's what they have claimed the
the publications al-jazeera and some
australian publication
what uh
what is the truth behind this
do we see anything on social media from
the people of agalega of that island
i mean
a couple of journalists or reporters go
and make a claim on behalf of somebody
else
and we know that these are propaganda
mouthpieces of various
forces
we need to be a little careful about
what we believe
it's very easy to manipulate public
opinion now what's happening there
controversy theory controversies and
conspiracy theories and like like is
being mentioned here
uh so what is the truth obviously india
is built building some sort of military
facility there
obviously the mauritius government is
fine with that now what is the
relationship like is india building the
airstrip for free we don't know
neither the indian government nor the
mauritius government has issued any
clarifications
but india does not
uh
engage in such activities
uh without fair compensation to any
country whether it is oman the duke port
whether it is iran chabahar whether it
is anything else
we typically have a good relationship
with the government we typically do
things that are of mutual benefit to
both countries and if we lease some
island or some some piece of land or
whatever india typically pays for that
india always pays for that so despite
the fact that no information is
available i can
i think we can safely say that whatever
india and mauritius are doing it is
something that's of mutual benefit india
and mauritius have very close relations
india has in the past uh
offered various uh coast guard vessels
to mauritius even a couple of
helicopters if i'm not mistaken and
india has always uh regarded mauritius
as a
sort of a country that falls within its
fear within its own
national interest or sphere of influence
not that india is trying to influence
the internal matters of mauritius that's
never happened
but there is obviously
uh
a whole history behind this and very
close ties between the people
the majority population of mauritius is
of indian origin i think uh slightly
less than half
so clearly there is a uh
deep in ancient history behind this so
uh
the reason why india is doing this
so we don't know whether india is paying
or not most likely obviously india is
being and obviously it's something that
benefits mauritius as well as india
now why is india doing this why is india
building an airstrip or some sort of uh
marine base
in the agalega islands well it's very
clear why if you look at the geography
of this region it's smack bang in the
middle of the indian ocean
yeah
and the indian ocean region is something
that the chinese have been eyeing for
the past decade or so they are trying to
build a network of
uh naval bases dual use bases the
so-called string of pearls so the
chinese bases there is one in djibouti i
have shown this in the past i will not
go into that right now there is one in
djibouti there is one in
gwadar pakistan
there is one
in hambantota
here it is in sri lanka they have
acquired this on a 99 year lease
they have been in talks with the
bangladesh government for one of their
ports maybe something with definitely
something with the myanmar government as
well
and again uh
they are trying to influence countries
like
thailand
and indonesia etc for such activities
and
even with madagascar i believe the the
chinese are trying to
acquire
some ports for
either
uh commercial purposes or dual use
purposes so the chinese are essentially
trying to encircle india and acquire a
significant strategic footprint naval
footprint in the indian ocean region
india needs to keep an eye on what the
chinese are doing and india needs to
build its own network
of sorts if possible so one sec is i
mean the the agalega islands
represents one of those investments that
india is making and obviously it is not
something that is that is being stolen
from mauritius it's being done with the
government of mauritius uh with with
their go ahead
so
india also has a
smaller network of bases or or
acquisitions in this region for instance
in oman we have the
port that india is developing
in india in iran we have chabahar which
i'm not sure what the status is like
iran is now very strongly pro-china so
that may not be the case
sri lanka and india have good relations
so sri lanka then we have the
andaman and nicobar islands which belong
to india themselves india itself
and various singapore also is favorably
inclined towards india the philippines
vietnam
japan and so on
so india also has
a footprint in this region
we cannot
quite say that india is encircling china
some people try to bring mongolia also
into that
that's not quite how it is but
so india is trying
to create its own
uh eyes and ears
in the indian ocean region india always
says that the indian ocean region is a
strategic backyard well india is now
putting its money where its mouth is
just slogans don't make the indian ocean
your strategic backhand you
actually have to invest in
infrastructure so that's what india is
doing so uh that is the story in brief
and uh
so that's what it is india is not
stealing any land from mauritius india
is not doing something that is against
the more national interest of more
issues it is something that's mutually
beneficial for both countries i'm sure
india is giving
more than enough more than a proper fair
compensation for the land it is acquired
and
it will
offer some some sort of benefits to
mauritius as well so that's what i can
say in brief right that's the background
about this story
okay um
interesting story here interesting
comment mr abhijit this is by mr ashok
churasama
mr abhijit you're totally uninformed and
misguided please talk on something based
on truths and fact gandhi was not
becoming overnight leader have you read
him read about him in details please re
please read about him if you don't have
time watch the movie gandhi at least
we'll give you some glimpse of what
gandhi was you have very little
knowledge about the history of
independence please make yourself more
knowledgeable i get this these comments
every day
please read you are not
you're not sufficiently informed you are
misinformed you know nothing you you
should read a little bit so that you
will gain some knowledge that's the kind
of comment i get all the time
so this is one such comment by mr ashok
churasuma who looks like a very
distinguished
gentleman
so uh firstly i would like to say that
you do not acquire knowledge about
history from watching movies
or watching tv series lots of people
tell me you're that i am wrong because
the ma whatever series they have seen
about the mahabharata or the romans
showed something else so whatever i'm
saying is wrong that's one
thing that i get all the time and this
is another one watch the movie gandhi
then you will know about mr gandhi do
you know what the movie gandhi was like
ask yourself this this this question
how come see the first of all this movie
gandhi
was a
co-production between india and the
british
the producer and director was richard
attenborough
it was british right there was a
significant british hand in this it was
all the
much of the work was done by
british artists
and there was some cooperation between
the indian government the british
government in this
the indian government of see this movie
was released in 1982 i think the indian
government of the time
is believed to have
funded at least uh
offered at least one third
of the movie's funding
right now the question
nobody asks
is why did the british make no movie
about sabah chandra bose
why is that
why did the british make no movie about
bhagat singh
or veer savarkar
why only about mr gandhi
and if you if you watch the movie it's
it's a geography of mr gandhi it's
portraying him as a saint essentially
right
so
it it
does not offer anything any gray areas
or anything about mr gandhi in his life
and so on so that is one thing first of
all that we have to ask ourselves
that why why
do the british
extol
the the virtues of mr gandhi and why did
they never make a movie about sabah
chandra bose or anybody else
well the truth is that they never saw mr
bose
is there any as
some
they always so bose as the real enemy
bose wished to overthrow the british
through military means
and he actually tried to do that he put
his life on the line and we we know how
it went
so bose tried to overthrow the british
by taking the help of the axis powers
because my enemy's enemy is my friend
that's how it works
now
if you if you want to read about mr
gandhi and see what actual historians
have to say
then look at people who who don't regard
him as a saint and have a more balanced
view
let me uh
so there is this british author called
patrick
french he's a very very uh
very well regarded historian
an accomplished historian let's see what
mr
richard french has to say about mr
gandhi
so he was a widely operated not india
smiling saying this is what
sorry patrick french patrick french has
to say
so there's a whole article over here
um
it goes into various things about
personal life of mr gandhi which i am
not really that much interested in
now
let's let's read this paragraph shall we
yeah this one here
i hope you can all see it on the screen
it says an important origin of the myth
was rich in richard attenborough's 1982
film gandhi take the episode when the
newly arrived gandhi is ejected from a
first-class railway carriage at peter
maritzburg after a white passenger
objects to sharing space with a
in fact
gandhi's demand to be allowed to travel
first class was accepted by the railway
company
rather than marking the start of a
campaign against racial operation
as legend has it
this episode was the start of a campaign
to extend racial segregation in south
africa
gandhi was adamant that respectable
indians should not be obliged to use the
same facilities as raw cafes or black
people
he petitioned the authorities in the
port city of durban where he practiced
law to end the indignity of making
indians use the same entrance to the
post office as black people
he and he counted it as a victory when
three doors were introduced one for
europeans one for asiatics or indians
and one for natives or black people
so mr gandhi was not trying to end
racial segregation
in south africa he was trying to extend
racial segregation in south africa he
was of the opinion that black people are
the lowest of the lot racially
indians are above the black people and
the europeans are the predominating race
that is what
mr gandhi was of that was his opinion
and that was what he campaigned for
right
and let's take the le take a look at the
last paragraph although mr gandhi may
have looked like a saint in an outfit
designed to represent the poor people of
rural india
he was above all
a wily operator and tactician having
lived in britain and south africa he was
familiar with the system he was
attempting to subvert he knew how to
undermine the british when to press an
advantage and when to withdraw little
wonder that one british provincial
governor described mr gandhi as being
cunning as a cart load of monkeys that
is what the one british provincial
governor said that's not what i am
saying all right
now mr french seems to be of the opinion
that the mr gandhi was trying to subvert
the system of the british and trying to
overthrow the british which may not
quite be the case but anyway
that's how it is so here is a different
perspective
by a historian by a british historian
so i would uh strongly urge people to
look at the 360 degree perspective when
it comes to mr gandhi there are a couple
of books everybody talks about one is
the experiments with truth one is
something else by
what mr guha or whatever
and uh some such things i would
recommend that why don't you
read the actual writings of mr gandhi
because indians are obsessed with
people's words so why don't you read
what mr gandhi actually wrote and all of
his uh
all of his writings are actually
available
in the public domain google it i'm not
going to spoon feed you
i get
people always ask me where's the
evidence for what you're saying why
don't you do a little bit of work on
your own whatever i'm telling you why
don't you grow why don't you cross
reference it and cross check it
all the evidence is out there in the
public domain use google
and don't use wikipedia use actual
sources that that are reliable
use google whatever questions you type
over here in the comments you can type
them in google and see what google
throws up try to do a little bit of
research on your own that's how you
learn
how long will you
get answers from me i mean i'm happy to
answer as many questions as i can
but
i would be really happy if some of you
would actually learn to do a little bit
of searching and research on your own
all the information is out there all the
voluminous and copious writings of mr
gandhi are all available in the public
domain you can see his opinions
expressed over there his attitudes and
his opinions about black people about
south africa about various other things
it's all there in the public domain the
entire record he was a
mr gandhi despite being an activist of
freedom fighters supposedly and whatever
not he found the time to write
thousands of pages of notes and letters
and whatnot and it's all available in
the public domain
so look it up
and discover mr gandhi in his own words
what he was like right so please don't
tell me to watch a movie and learn about
mr gandhi please please i have done a
little bit of reading of my own in my
life so thank you
and i i mean no disrespect personally to
mr
chudasama
none at all i'm just see
this is something i've seen lots of
times lots of times i've seen
when i go um
when i do
some kind of public appearance or some
kind of speech or whatever
there's a q a session and lots of
distinguished elderly gentlemen
express this sort of opinion
i remember once somebody said that
there must be something really wrong
with indian culture that india produced
nothing of any value in the scientific
world in the last 2000 years
how misinformed people are
and it's not their fault that they're
misinformed it's the indian education
system that has made them believe all
this and after a certain age i've
noticed again and again
that after a certain age people are just
unwilling to change their opinion even
when you show them the facts in the
facts
there in the face
it's the uncles and aunties generation
which refuses
to change their worldview even when you
show them the facts
so i'm glad most of my viewers are
younger people
so
that's how it is right so that's what i
have to say about this matter
okay amay says
why
japan didn't invade russia in world war
ii at the uh the time of german invasion
on russia
they can they they could have gained
things like oil natural resources etc
okay it's a very clumsily worded
question but an excellent question this
is a very intelligent question and a
great question even though it's worded
slightly uh awkwardly uh
why did japan
not invade the ussr
in the during the time of the second
world war when germany invaded the ussr
so they could have gained lots of things
like natural resources territory oil and
so on good question good question very
good question let's go to the map and
take a look at what the geography is
like so that you can understand why this
question is being asked it's a very good
question let's take a look at the map
once again
so here is the map effect yeah here it
is now
so this is japan
as you can see this here is japan
are the bunch of islands to the east of
asia to the east of korea
and to the north of japan there is
disputed territory this is the island of
i believe hokkaido
north of hokkaido is the sakhalin
peninsula of the
island
of sakha sakhalin
which is russian territory today and
there are all these islands over here
which are
disputed islands they are
held by russia the kuril islands but the
japanese claim them okay that's a
different story that is something the
so the japanese russian conflict dates
back back to the early 1900s
1904 1905 there was this naval war
between japan and russia and the
russians lost disastrously the japanese
won they became became regarded as one
of the great maritime powers and one of
the world's great powers
in 1905
now
so
and and to the east of japan as you can
see there is this massive
massive geographical entity which is
russia today which was the ussr uh in
the second world war
right
and the japanese had a very powerful
expeditionary army they had they had one
of the major most powerful navies in the
world at the time
so the question is very good why did
japan decide not to invade the ussr when
the germans had already
begun their invasion launched their
invasion of the ussr
so the germans
had invaded the ussr from the west and
it was an excellent time for the
japanese to
to start a two-front war like we talked
about in india right but they did not do
it why was that so
um
in 1939
i believe the japanese had already
invaded uh
eastern china manchuria present-day
china manchuria they created a puppet
regime called the manchoku regime and
they had
also conquered parts of
northern china
and mongolia at the time was under
the u.s under under the control of the
ussr now the japanese
army
tried to uh
invade soviet-controlled territory and
there were these border clashes there
was a there were a few battles almost
like a war between the japanese army and
the ussr
under admiral zhukov i believe
he was commanding the ussr army
and the russians were defeated
thoroughly
they got a bad whipping in this
in this brief war
at the time there were two schools of
thought in the japanese military
one was there it was a very powerful
military
and they had a massively powerful navy
at the time so one school of thought
was the northern expansion school of
thought the one portion of the japanese
military wanted to expand into eurasia
from the north which means take over
manchuria take over parts of the ussr
take over eastern ussr and go further
west from there onwards that's a massive
huge territory right so there was one
school of thought the other school of
thought
in the japanese military was to expand
in the south
take out parts of china maybe whole of
china the whole of china
south east asia and advance into india
so that was the other school of thought
now after the
disastrous defeat of the japanese
military
in mongolia
the consequence of that was that the
school of thought that said japan should
expand in this in the south that school
of thought prevailed
and that's why the japanese military the
japanese leadership decided to
not go ahead with invading russia
but go ahead with invading china and
southeast asia
and that's what they did and of course
the majority of the resources were
available
in china and southeast asia right so
that's why they did that and they had a
very successful
brutal and rapid advance
they swept aside the chinese forces the
swept
uh the british forces in
southeast asia in singapore etc and they
they marched onwards to the doorstep of
india they actually entered india in
nagaland and manipur and it was even
with the international army of sebastian
reports and they also took over the
andaman nicobar islands but eventually
from that portion onwards they were
beaten back and that was the beginning
of the end of the imperial japanese
occupation of
southern and southeastern asia
so that is
in brief
why
the japanese decided not
to invade the ussr but decided to invade
southern southeast asia and
go further westwards towards india
okay this is a question by rama lakshmi
who
i would like to appreciate because he
is
he puts up the um time stamps all the
time thank you so much ramadan i really
appreciate that so the question is uh we
know that brahmanas in ancient india
were knowledge bearers uh but
if a person from chatria
wanted to study
rather than then take a place in the
military was there a provision for doing
that similarly for brahmin as well
listen
so
caste we talk about caste here there was
no caste system in india there was a
varnajati system in india okay let's
let's go into that first what is the
varanasi system let me give a weird
example but i think it will make sense
let's say there's a person from
canada
who becomes a hindu who starts
practicing hinduism
right
and that person is a school teacher
today
so
based on that what we can say that the
person's jathi is canadian
and varna is a brahmana because that
person is a is a person who imparts
knowledge
let's say a person from italy
italy
starts practicing hinduism and that
person is a soldier
so that person's jaati will be italian
or roman or whatever you want to call it
and their varna will be chatria let's
say a person from russia today decides
to start practicing hinduism so their
jati will be russian
their varna will be a
laborer right a carpenter or whatever so
that will be sudra
and let's say a person from germany
starts to practice hinduism
and that person is a
business person
so their jati will be german and their
varna will be vaishya so that's how it
always worked but this person who is a
business person decides to
start
become
decides to become a teacher then their
varna will change
from asia
to to brahman based on their occupation
and their aptitude so that's how it
works and that's how it always was in
india
uh if you look at greek accounts from
the mauryan times there were seven
divisions in indian society not four
seven divisions i've spoken about that
in the past but uh later on it was four
divisions the four uh varnas right
now there are lots of examples where
people were born into a certain varna
and they moved on to a different verna
based on their
occupation and their aptitude and all
that for instance there were several
kings of vijayanagar
let's talk about the great king krishna
devaraya
he was not born
the king the great emperor of the
vijayanagara empire from the
15th and 16th centuries yes
he was not born at chatham he was born
into a different varna
but he was the emperor and he and he had
all the qualities of akshatriya
let's talk about chandragupta maurya we
don't even know what his varna was
he was most likely an orphan kid who was
raised to the status of emperor by the
great vishnu tanaka so he we don't know
what his birth varna was but he lived as
a truck trier let's take the example of
the uh
of the brahman dronacharya he was a
brahmana he was a teacher he taught
martial arts and various other things
and he fought in the mahabharat war
and as he
because he fought he
acted as a kshatriya right so that's how
it is
so varna is not cast caste is something
the british created after they came to
india and that's the one of the biggest
causes of all the societal problems we
have in india today and they they
ossified that system the british so
varna is not cast and jaati is a whole
different thing right jaati is something
you're born with and which stays with
you it's your lineage
right it's your lineage varna is what
you do your occupation
you go be a soldier you're a chatria you
go and teach you or you become a scholar
you are a brahmana you become a business
person
or a vegetable vendor or whatever you
want you are a vision if you want to
become a laborer or something you that
that makes you a a shudra and shudra is
not something like it's a bad thing it's
just four different uh
essentially occupations classes of
occupations so varna is not cast even
the gods in india were classified into
warner's right agni is supposed to be a
brahmana indra is obviously akshatriya
the warrior god and the god push on is
and so on so that's how it was so in
ancient india before the past 1000 years
of humiliation before that terrible
period there was
no such ossification of the of the
vernas you could go into
you may be born into a certain verna
into a certain family that practices a
certain occupation but based on the
aptitude you showed in school etc you
could go into something else that was
perfectly fine take the chinese pilgrim
shwanzang who came to india did he have
any varna he was a foreigner foreigners
i mean we don't even know whether
foreigners have his jaati was tang
chinese
his varna based on his
deeds and actions became was became
brahmana because he was a scholar
right so that's how it always went
we need to understand that
and the problem is
i will get a lot of pushback about what
i've just said people will say you are
whatever right
i don't blame the people who do that
they have been taught certain things
since childhood since the time they were
three or five years old the education
system takes care of that and the
education system has been
the the syllabus and the textbooks have
been written by india's enemies
that's what we are living through
our education system is in the hands of
our enemies
our entertainment industry is
essentially in the hands of
international uh forces forces that are
inimical to indian national interest and
culture i would i'm not saying everybody
is like that but many of them are like
that many of them
and the entire education system since
the 1970s has been
under a marxist stranglehold and we know
what their attitude is like so please
don't please take a bigger picture
approach look at actual original sources
look at what the foreigners said about
india
before the era of invasions before they
passed millennium feminisation what did
the greeks say about india what did the
chinese saber india what did the these
kitchens say about india and so on so
forth what did the persians have to say
about india what did the arabs say about
india the overwhelming
the entire account over these centuries
in millennia has always been extremely
extremely positive
so
it is time
hopefully soon to decolonize and
decontaminate the indian education
system
right
says jai hinson sir can pakistan
disintegrate into three countries like
pakistan's ex-prime minister sheri imran
khan said
pakistan the only
thing that holds that is holding
pakistan together is external forces
pakistan is very useful
as a counter balance to india pakistan
is very useful from time to time when
somebody wants to hurt india or bleed
india
pakistan is very useful for forces that
seek to keep india off balance and
always worry about the western border
in the past it was the u.s that funded
and financed and aided and abetted
pakistan
today it's china
in the future it could be the u.s again
who knows we don't know how it goes
um so
the only reason why pakistan
is held together as a unified country
is because of external forces they want
pakistan to stay together that's why
they prop up the army which owns the
country
there is no democracy over there there
are prime ministers that come and go
come and go it makes no difference they
don't really hold any real power
they may have money they have no power
the power lies with the pakistan army
right
so uh the moment pakistan is no longer
useful for anybody it's gonna
disintegrate
it's gonna disintegrate and i i haven't
i've said this many times i have nothing
against the people of pakistan
i wish them nothing
i have no ill will towards them i hope
they live great lives and all that and
their good futures
of whatever kind they want
but pakistan is a problem for india
and
india should
find a way
of resolving this problem once and for
all it is
historically indian territory that has
been taken over
expropriated from india
against without consulting the people of
india so it's not a legitimate nation
right it is
territory that is historically indian
territory it is the territory the sacred
territory of our ancestors for at least
10 000 years
so uh yes
like shri imran khan ji said pakistan
can certainly disintegrate into three or
more countries i mean which three
countries sindhu desh is one
balochistan is another
what else do we have
pakistani punjab is the third and
pashtun is the fourth which may
reintegrate itself with afghanistan so
it's not three it accumulates four but
yeah
disintegration is always on the cards
but right now pakistan is useful
pakistan is useful for certain
major foreign powers
to keep
india
counterbalanced
to ensure that india doesn't rise too
much
and it's useful for more than one
foreign power even today
so as long as that is there pakistan is
going to stay in one piece but once
india rises beyond a certain point it
may not be possible for pakistan to
remain united because there is no real
thing that keeps pakistan united except
for the army in external forces
okay next question
oops long question umai the rafiq says
i'm from afghanistan living in canada i
was very surprised when i heard an
indian friend of mine
considering the mughals and afghans to
be the same to my shock he started
praising urdu
i took my time and explained to him that
afghans and mughals fought many wars
we speak pashto not urdu so i wonder why
is it that afghan indians often brush
afghans pakistanis with the same brush
in afghanistan people are very pro have
a very positive view towards india
very interesting uh
insight from somebody who's an afghan
and pashtun i expect so
this is all because of the indian
education system
which does not teach the true history of
india
right
afghanistan the people of afghanistan
they fought the turks multiple times
like you said they fought what's his
name timur the the the tyrant
timur the lame timur lung
who passed through afghanistan
on his way towards delhi where he
committed genocide
right
that brutal barbarian
timur
so the afghans resisted that invasion
the afghans resisted the so-called
mughals who are actually turks
the afghans fought against
their turks and proved tried to prevent
their invasion into the indian
subcontinent
and at one point in time
in the 16th century if i'm not mistaken
the
king of afghanistan was a hindu himachal
vikramaditya
his army was made up of pashtuns muslims
but he was their king
he was the successor to sheriff
and he actually
reclaimed the throne of delhi and was
installed as the last hindu emperor the
last native emperor
of the indian subcontinent of india
and
he
uh
eventually fought the the
the
invader akbar
and he received a stray arrow to the to
the eye and that's what killed him so he
was unlucky that he got killed but
that's how it went
and then this uh this guy akbar he had
the dead body of hemu
decapitated and his head was sent to
kabul
to terrorize the local people that see
what we did to your king
right so
the afghans 500 even 500 years ago
regarded themselves as natives of the
indian
subcontinent it's only in the durrani
era
that the
final break kind of sort of happened and
today afghans consider themselves to be
completely different from indians
so um
but the truth is that the afghans
especially the pashtuns
have
very ancient
uh cultural and
ethnic ties with the rest of india
i have in the past showed genetic papers
that
demonstrate that the pashtuns are an
extension of the north indian population
their culture is very much
the culture
of the indian subcontinent i'm not
talking about the islamic culture which
has been imposed upon them in the past
thousand years the deeper
cultural traditions and all the
attendance and various other things the
kind of dress is the where
the uh
the code of honor that they have
some of it comes from their deeper past
and
the city of kandahar
more than a thousand years ago was
called the city of rajputs
so
that is the true history of afghanistan
and now when it comes to pakistanis
pakistanis are genetically and
ethnically indian
but
there is a whole history between
pakistan and afghanistan which is more
recent in origin it dates back to the
conquests of maharaja ranjit singh
the sikh king
who
launched multiple punitive expeditions
into what is now afghanistan captured
large parts of
pashtun or afghan territory and that
became the durant line because once the
original thing died the british
destroyed the sikh kingdom took over the
whole thing and they used the
the border of ranjit singh as the de
facto border between india and
afghanistan
after india's partition that became the
border between pakistan and afghanistan
and much of the north west frontier
province is historically well pashtun
territory so that's why the afghans and
pakistanis have this issue
so yes the the afghans don't speak urdu
which is a amalgam of
ancient prakrit uh basha
of us of a certain upper branch of
praket language with
turkic
arabic
and persian words
thrown into the mix that's what urdu is
pashto is not urdu
is very different
is more like a dhardik language
it's like an indo-iranian language it
has elements of persian it has elements
of the old sanskrit grammar in it
uh if you replace the various persian
words with sanskrit it will make a lot
of sense actually and so on so that's
that's the story
so uh
that is the truth
that uh afghans are not turks
the pashtuns are not mughals in any way
whatsoever and the pashtuns are not very
fond of urdu just like we in india are
not very fond of urdu so that's how it
is
okay this is a question from twitter the
poll lady asks why are indian parents
especially government employees so
obsessed with american ideally iv ivy
league universities and this is a good
question
um
so all indians want their all indian
parents want their kids to do well and
until i mean even today you want to do
well you need to get out of india
because india's living standards and
wages etc are quite low india is still a
developing country a so-called
low-income or third world country
so if you can go and live in the west
and
earn money there then you have a much
better standard of living and quality of
life and all that and
the key to doing that is to getting a
degree in an american university or an
australian university or some western
university and among all of these
universities the
universities the so-called ivy league
universities are the cream of the korean
the kremlin
right the best of the blood of the lord
so that's why indian parents
have their greatest dream is to see
their kid
their son daughter whatever graduate
from an ivy league first of all get
admission to an ivy league university
like higher like harvard or
stanford or whatever right
even dartmouth college i believe is an
ivy league institution whatever so get
admission there and get a degree from
there and so there are two things one is
that it gives you a higher chance of
succeeding in the
in the legacy academic system because if
you had a degree from one of these
places you would get a high paying job
in the us
and secondly it's a question of prestige
my kid graduated from an ivy league or
my kid got admission to stanford or
harvard or whatever right it's a
question of prestige
so human beings are motivated by two
main things
one is money the other thing is status
so this is something that has to do with
something to do with both there's
another thing as well
she mentions government employees now um
i don't know if it is the fbi or the cia
most likely the cia that revealed this
that one of the best ways of getting
a person
from a third world country
to cooperate with the u.s
especially if you want that person to
do something against their own country
and help the us one of the best ways of
doing this is to offer their children or
one of their child children
admission
free of cost
to an ivy league university
you get that done for them they will do
anything for you they will betray their
own country their own people their own
government for that
so that is something the fbi the cia i
believe
revealed or leaked or something like
that
and that applies to various third world
countries low-income countries etc and
india is very much part of that so it
would be interesting i'm not saying
anything anybody should do this but it
would be interesting to see
how many indian
government employees
have children who are currently studying
in the ivy league universities or who
have had such children who have studied
there in the past that would be really
interesting to see
okay
next question
jay kate says can you tell everyone
about
the biot british indian ocean territory
how can the u.s or the uk use these
islands against us whenever needed
let's go to the map
the british indian ocean territory where
is it it is called the chagos
archipelago
south of the maldives this is india you
go southwards
you have the lakshadweep islands
further south you have the maldives the
capital is malay
and
you go further south you have the
british indian ocean territory
which is part of the chagos archipelago
right the chago chago archipelago
now
when it comes to this british indian
ocean territory the biot it is an
extension
of the lakshadweep and maldives islands
that's what it is
you could consider this archipelago to
be the southernmost component
of the lakshadweep maldives system
now if we go further into this place as
you can see uh let me show the satellite
imagery whatever is available
there is a major air base here
the diego garcia airport this place is
called diego garcia
so there is an airport here there are
various
residential facilities and various other
things which we don't quite know what
they are
there is uh
supermarkets this looks like a
residential place
and so on and so forth
so as you can see this is an extensively
developed
place
and it is a naval and military
installation who is operating this
it is united states that's operating it
who does it belong to it still belongs
to the united kingdom
to the british
this is the leftover of the colony
legacy
uh i wonder why india did not
reincorporate these
these uh british possessions into
india i suppose india was
not in a position to choose because we
were being handed over
it was a transfer of power which was
give which was happening on the terms of
the british not on india's terms and we
did not snatch independence from the
british we received it from the british
as a gift or as whatever else like some
people say
so that's what it is right that's what
the chagos archipelago is now let's take
um
let me show you something else
right so the strategic importance
of this place so diego garcia
is about 2 000
this is in miles you can convert to
kilometers we wish this is 2000 miles
from somalia
2 300 miles from aadhan in yemen
2700 miles from bahrain and qatar
3000 miles from kabul a thousand miles
from india roughly
uh and the various distances are over
here to perth darwin australia east
timor taiwan straight etc
it's a very important strategic location
in the middle of the indian ocean right
that's what it is
and
this is the kind of uh
installations that we have there is a
base there there's a runway
there are approximately 3000 u.s and uk
military personnel and civilian
operators
and that's what it is right
so that is a little bit about the uh
diego garcia
territory which the british still
control
which belongs to britain but it is
operated by the us
because
britain the uk is a u.s basal state it's
part of the same empire so the u.s
operates this the majority of the
personnel there military personnel are
americans or british who are working for
the u.s for the for the same empire
so it is a very strategically located
place it's a thousand miles 1500
kilometers or so from
from the indian mainland
and
it's a very important military military
installation for the u.s they can
control much of the indian ocean region
from there
and they would have military aircraft in
the ships and warships etc docked over
there so that is what it is it's not for
use against india per se
it's just to have a very strategic
position location
in the indian ocean
so that's what
and they have similar such bases in guam
in the pacific ocean
and various other locations i'm talking
about the us
so it is it has been part of the policy
to have military bases all across the
world they have i believe the us
has more than 800 military bases
installations all across the world
and some of the most important ones in
the oceans are guam in the pacific ocean
and diego garcia
in the indian ocean now the history is
interesting the original inhabitants
of diego garcia of the chago archipelago
were
a
native population which included indians
or people of mixed native and indian
origin
right
these people were forcibly evicted
from their ancestral homeland by the
british
in the 20th century and they were
forcibly look relocated to mauritius or
some something like that
and
they have been
demanding justice they have been
demanding
that they be re that the islands be
reinstated to them
and i believe there was a court case in
the uk and the islanders won the court
case
and yet nothing has been done
so this territory has been stolen from
the natives
it has been stolen unjustly unfairly
from the natives by the british and it
is now used by the by the us
so this is stolen territory which is
something the americans and the british
have been doing have done for the past
three four five centuries right
so you can look up you can read up more
about this but that's the little bit i
would like to offer to you about this
particular matter let's go into the next
question
they just says hypothetically what will
happen if two black holes collide
will they coexist or form a more giant
black hole or get neutralized in some
way and become stars planets something
else
when two black holes collide they merge
and they become a larger black hole the
mass of the resultant single black hole
is slightly less than the sum of the
masses of the two original black holes
some of the mass is
given off in the form of energy
in the form of gravitational waves when
the collision the in spiral happens and
the eventual merger happens so it's not
quite a collision
it's a process in which the black holes
come together and they start orbiting
each other
and the
radius of the orbit keeps decreasing
over time the orbits go faster and
faster and faster and eventually the the
two black holes merge
and they give off a massive tsunami of
gravitational waves so some of the mass
is
is given off i mean this in the form of
energy of the gravitational waves
so you can think of black holes as
well one of the analogies i can offer is
to regard a black hole as a drop of
fluid
right a drop of fluid so there are two
drops of fluid which eventually merge
together
so
it will not get neutralized like you see
or become star or planet it will become
just a larger black hole they will merge
together
okay karthik says which is our closest
galaxy
um
which is our closest galaxy is it
andromeda or is it
major
good question so um
canis major is not a galaxy canis major
is a constellation
the word for constellation in sanskrit
or hindi or whatever is nakshatra
right so that's what kinase major is
it's not a galaxy
now uh which is the closest galaxy the
closest
well andromeda is the closest proper
galaxy it's about two and a half million
light years away from our from our
location
so that is the closest proper galaxy but
there are two other galaxies that are
closer to it which are
dwarf galaxies which is the large
magellanic cloud and the small
magellanic cloud so the large magellanic
cloud is about 160 000 light years away
from us and the smaller one is about 200
000 light years away from us
these two dwarf galaxies orbit our
galaxy the milky way so that is
what it is right
next question is by ramalakshmi
the 9 m 730
borre vestnik is said to be a
nuclear-powered
nuclear missile which could have partly
unlimited range if the question is if
such a missile hits the planet there
will be radiation if such a missile is
intercepted then there could be
radioactive waste it is directly
released into the atmosphere what do you
what do you think about this missile and
should india
also look into it okay
so not much is known about this missile
the existence of this missile was i
believe
revealed or announced i think in 2018
2019 by mr putin
so we don't quite have much information
in the public domain about how this
missile works what it is like
it is believed that it has a nuclear
ramjet so a ramjet is something that uh
accelerates the missile beyond max mach
1 mach 2. uh the brahmos missile
has a ramjet it's a two-stage missile
there's an initial missile the initial
solid fuel motor that takes the rock the
missile past the speed of sound
and from there onwards the ram judge can
take over which
requires supersonic speeds
so the brahmos has a conventional ramjet
a chemical ramjet
it is believed that this
9m730 has a nuclear
ramjet which
does not have chemical fuel but which
uses the
the uh
heat of a nuclear reaction typically a
fusion reaction to to
accelerate
or or to power the
the uh missile to mach 2 or up to max 6
i believe so that's a nuclear lambda the
heat of the nuclear reaction uh
pushes the speed pushes the air
to to beyond supersonic speeds
uh
and it has more or less unlimited
unlimited range it can fly for several
days without stop it can
circle the globe multiple times so which
means it has
loitering capability
it can
have an unpredictable path if that is
programmed into it
and it has essentially unlimited range
because of this
if such a missile
hits the planet obviously there will be
radiation
but such a missile is designed to carry
a nuclear warhead not a conventional
warhead
so uh if it is inter intercepted then
there will be radiation radiate
release of radiation and if it hits the
target and the nuclear warhead explodes
then once again there's gonna be
radioactive fallout so that's what
happens anyway
when a nuclear bomb is either used in
warfare or it is tested in the
atmosphere an atmospheric test
so that is what the missile is that is
the purpose it's
its purpose is to deliver nuclear
warheads not conventional warheads
and
so that's what we know about the missile
that's what is believed
to be known about the missile
should india look into that i don't
think india needs to look into that
we
are not an expansionist nation we don't
have
um
threats globally as such we have
local threats
the two threats are pakistan which is a
minor threat in china which is the real
threat
so that is what we need to be uh
that's what we need to plan for and we
don't need such a missile a nuclear
power powered missile to take care of
these threats we have our own uh
ballistic missile and strategic missile
program which is more than adequate
to uh safeguard our national interests
so that's what i can say
pranay says can we ever have an indian
subcontinent union consisting of india
pakistan bangladesh
sri lanka nepal bhutan with open borders
like european union will that boost the
economy of all nations
would you like an open border with
pakistan
bangladesh well when it comes to
bangladesh we more or less have an open
border for whatever reason
but would you really want an open border
with pakistan
does it make any sense as of today
so uh it is not possible
as of today at least it won't be
possible in the next 50 years until
pakistan can be suitably
de-radicalized and de-terrorized
de-terroristized or whatever you want to
call it right
pakistan is is a terror factory
it is one of the biggest threats to
world peace
i'm not talking about the people but the
establishment the military and the
terrorist infrastructure and all that
that's what it is even hillary clinton
said that the pakistanis are breeding
snakes in their in the backyard for use
against afghanistan and india right so
pakistan is a huge problem we can never
have an open border system with pakistan
as long as this this persists
we already have something called sark
right sark
south asian association for regional
cooperation which is no longer really
functional because of pakistan
so in the future someday
it would be great to reunify the
subcontinent into one single
political entity that would certainly
boost the economy of the entire region
i don't mind having open borders with
nepal which we already do
with sri lanka
which to some extent we we may have
and with uh bhutan even myanmar
what else do we have with nepal we
already have it so these nations with
them we don't we could have an open
border kind of agreement arrangement
with myanmar there is a certain issue
going on there so we may have to be
careful about that
but certainly with bhutan certainly with
nepal certainly with sri lanka
and that would certainly boost the
economies of those places
now remember
the
main engine that drives the economy of
the subcontinent is india itself
some people have pointed out that nepal
was never colonized by the british well
officially colonized by the british and
yet
despite nepal not being colonized no
wealth being extracted out of nepal
nepal is so poor today why is it so
it's because nepal
has always depended on the indian
economy nepal well people say nepal has
always been independent that's nonsense
nepal was always part of various indian
empires so nepal's economy has always
been dependent on the indian economy
so if there is an open border system it
will certainly benefit these small local
economies like nepal bhutan sri lanka
and so on it would be good for all of
them so eventually we would like to have
a system like that
when india rises to its full potential
today it is not possible right
donggar singh johan says what's the most
effective way to control population in a
country like india
and how can we ensure that we have a
significant proportion of youth in our
population
well you know what recently the news has
emerged that india's total
fertility rate has slipped below the
replacement level
the replacement level
is 2.1 children statistically per woman
india's fertility rate tfr is now two
children per woman
which is below the replacement rate of
course there are certain demographics
within india which have a much higher
fertility rate we're not going we're not
going into that but overall
statistically india's total fertility
rate is now for the first time in
in living memory
dipped below the the replacement level
so we don't need to worry further about
controlling population it's already
under control
now what happens when your two tfr dips
below the replacement level what happens
is that after four five six decades your
population gets older and older and
older
that's what we are seeing in many
countries look at japan what happened
the japanese uh tfr began
i'm not sure i don't have the statistics
with me but the economy crashed after
the 1980s that's a whole different story
it was made to crash
and after that the country has gone into
a recession and the japanese population
is getting older and older and it's way
below the replacement rate the chinese
population has also gone below the
replacement rate and their population is
also getting older and older
the only way
to ensure that there is a significant
proportion of youth in your population
is to ensure that your
tfr is above replacement
at least 2.2 or more but now we are at
two so in the long run our population is
going to get older the the average age
of the population is going to get older
and older
so that's where we are and there are a
number of factors that contribute to
these things
and uh we could we could have a separate
session about that
um
the economy matters
the amount
in the past
uh things were different in india today
what hap what's happening is that we
have this
uh
ongoing and increasing urbanization of
the country
and now it's getting more and more
expensive to have children
just childbirth costs you a couple of
lakh rupees in a hospital that's what a
private hospital would extract out of
you
and then education has become so
expensive and the other factor is that
people are so busy you have to work a
nine-to-five job but in private uh
companies it's not nine to five it's
nine to seven or nine to nine sometimes
you know
and typically both husband and wife are
working so there is no no way for for
them to take care of their children
and today we don't have extended
families anymore we have nuclear
families so who's going to take care of
the kids
right because people are transplanted
from their native place to whatever
metropolitan city they are working on
working in
so both husband and wife
both parents are busy very busy they're
trying to make a career
and there's no
there's not enough money to raise a
child and there's no time to take care
of a child so because of these factors
people are having fewer kids some people
are going childless out of choice or
whatever
and
so there's a there's multiple factors
like this
because of this india's
tfr has slipped below
replacement for the first time in living
memory
and if this continues india's population
in the in this coming century
by the 21st century is done india's
average age of the population could be
much
much more than what it is today i think
today the average age is 28 or so
in india
so in the future it could get older and
you know that's how it is so
so that's the answer to your question
sir
please answer this question it's very
important for me and for the other teams
too
okay
so long question
as the world is changing colleges aren't
the only medium to learn
we know how the thing is
we can literally learn anything for free
on the internet
there are many irrelevant subjects we
have to study in the colleges
the education system is faulty so what
should we do
instead of opting for a college should
we learn and enhance a la skill like
coding from a boot camp
which will save our money and even three
four years of our precious time
so that we can be financially stable and
add value to the country
what should be
what is the best thing please please
please please okay
yeah this is dilemma all lots of kids
face
the thing is this
in the us certain companies now let's
let's
take the example of tesla
elon musk's company
such companies they no longer require
you to have some kind of a degree
you don't need to have a degree to apply
for a position in that company and you
may be accepted even though you don't
have a degree they will put you through
a set of aptitude tests and interviews
and all that
and if you can demonstrate that you have
the skills that they need then they will
then you will be offered a job even if
you don't have a degree
in india that
that situation is still not there
indian companies private companies the
government sector is just
it's still
the it is still mired in the 19th
century 20th century world view so you
need degrees and all that all that stuff
even in the private sector
the people who run the private sector
most of the companies are uncles and
aunties so to say
and their attitudes are still very
antiquated so they the most important
thing for them is what degree do you
have what percentage of how much
how many ma what marks did you get did
you get first class distinction what did
and all that matters for them even
though the education system really
doesn't give you any real skills or
knowledge
so as of today in india
degrees still matter unfortunately it is
it is terrible that it but it is true
as of today if you want a good job in a
private company they're gonna the first
thing they're gonna ask you is show me
your degree
and what percentage did you get and all
that
until this attitude changes you will
need to go through college
unfortunately
right
uh maybe in the next decade or so
as more startups come up they will only
look for skills and not care about
degrees hopefully that happens soon but
as of today degrees are still
unfortunately important
so you have you have no choices of today
get your degree and also find the time
to acquire real skills like coding or
whatever something that is
gonna give you some real value to you
and whatever company or organization you
work for because at the end of the day
it's skills that matter
today you have all these kids who come
out of college with degrees who don't
know how to do anything
when they join a let's say a software
company or i.t company they have the
company has to teach them the skills
over a six month or so period and only
then can they start becoming productive
at the lowest level they're called
freshers i believe right
um
and most of them end up on bench or
whatever it takes a couple of years for
the person to become actually competent
in what he or she is doing that's a
waste incredible waste of time
and that's what the education system
does you get an mba or or
mca or whatever it is or a master's
degree or bachelor's degree or whatever
it's worth nothing in terms of skills
so unfortunately today
to ensure that you have the best shot at
a good career you will have to acquire
your degree
but also make sure that you go through
whatever
coding bootcamp or whatever it is and
acquire real skills as well so that when
you actually get a job you are ready
with the skills that they need that way
you will have a better uh you will have
an advantage of over your peers who only
have a degree but no skills
so that is the right answer as of today
hopefully in the next few years things
will change and you will no longer need
a degree i hope that happens tomorrow if
possible but
in the next decade at least
okay karan says what is the speed of the
expanding universe it's very simple the
speed of the expanding universe is the
hubble constant now there are two values
of the hubble constant one is a 73
kilometers per second per mega per sec
the other value
is 68 kilometers per second per mega per
second and why are the two values we
don't quite know this is called the
hubble tension i'll not go into that
so
let's let's take the first case 73
kilometers per second per mega per
second mega parsec is
a unit of distance a mega per sec is
3.26
million light years
okay
so
what does this mean 73 let me write it
down so that you can see
um can i write it somewhere
73 kilometers per second per mega per
sec
let me put this over here
is it visible
yes
so this is the hubble constant this is
the rate of expansion of the universe
what does this mean
so this changes
with distance
what this means is that
if
an object a star or a galaxy
is less than one mega per second away
from us
then that object is receding away from
us at a speed of 73 kilometers per
second
but if an object is 10 megaparsecs away
from us
then that object is receding away from
us at 730
kilometers per second
if something is a hundred megaparsecs
away from us
that object is receding away from us
it's 7
300 kilometers per second and so on
and there is a distance
beyond which objects are actually
receding away from us
faster than the speed of light
so that is what it is that is the speed
of the expanding universe in very very
very very
brief
right let's take the next question
swarupa says if various models
of scientists
like rutherford's model jj thompson's
model etc were really rejected
why were they taught to students in in
school okay
what he's referring to is the model of
the atom
so here's what happened
in the late 19th century j.j thomson
discovered the electron
the electron is a negatively charged
of subatomic particle right
so he discovered that there is something
called the electron
so he proposed the thompson model the
plum pudding model which says that in i
think the early 20th century which says
that electrons are like negatively
charged plums
embedded in a positively charged pudding
and that's what the atom is like
so that is the model he came up with
based on the best data or knowledge that
was available at the time
then
in 1911 or something
the positively charged nucleus was
discovered so every atom has a
positively charged nucleus and this was
discovered by rutherford marsden and
geiger
that put these guys put forth the
rutherford model
which says that there is that an atom is
like
a solar system a positively charged
nucleus and electrons negatively charged
electrons that go around it so that was
the rutherford model that was based on
the best knowledge and data that we had
at that time but then certain problems
happened because if electrons are going
in circles in orbits around the
the positively charged nucleus then
they're gonna lose energy and that they
should in spiral into the nucleus that
doesn't happen
then you had the bohr summer failed
explanation the rutherford model and so
on
which explained the red bug formula for
the spectral emission lines of hydrogen
and further improvements were done as
more information became available and
more theoretical improvements were done
so if we study all of these models
and how they were improved upon then we
actually learn how science is done we
understand the scientific method that's
why it's very important that these
things are taught these models were not
rejected
these models were iteratively improved
upon
eventually in the 1920s we had the birth
of the science of of quantum mechanics
which eventually became quantum field
theory
which is the most accurate
and successful theory of physics that we
have till date
part and so on so that's how
improvements are done that's how science
is
done and if you if we learn these models
then we actually get to learn the
scientific method and that is very
valuable for science students that's why
all of these models are taught in school
next question is by chandra shekhar
namaskarams
why should pure mathematics be funded
95 of pure mathematics papers have no
relevance nor are they nor do they have
any applicability in the present day
world
why should any government waste their
money funding these pure mathematicians
just because they are doing intellectual
gymnastics being a former mathematics
student myself i can assure you that
none of my
faculties or friends research papers
from top institutes are of any worth
their h index is approximately zero i
haven't seen those results be results
being used anywhere
it's just lying down as garbage
in some research journal has pure
mathematics lost its charm to computers
just like
how chess has withered away due to the
invention of
chess engines
a good question
why should pure mathematics be funded
see many of the
it's true that most
most of the research papers are worth
nothing
and they have no i would not say worth
nothing but whatever they're doing it
doesn't seem to have any real
application in the real world
as a physicist
i only use the math
that i need to solve the problem that
i'm working on i am not interested in
any other math
so i learn math as i go and i only use
what's needed so there's a whole toolkit
that physicists use we find that in
you'll find that in very various
textbooks about the about
mathematical methods of physics
um byron fuller etc so all of that is
useful in physics some of it has
applications in computer science and so
on but much of pure mathematics has no
applications anywhere as of today so why
should we fund it
yeah
you know when you
when you are mining gold
yeah
when you when you have a an operation at
a gold mine
what the machines do
is that they shovel up tons and tons of
dirt
and then all the dirt is protect
processed
and refined thoroughly
over a bunch of processes which are done
in sequence
and eventually what you find is that you
are able to extract a few grams of gold
per ton
of ore that is extracted
so for every thousand kilos of dirt that
you pull out of the mine you get a few
grams of of gold
and yet you do it
you go through all the dirt to get a few
grams of gold
so that's an analogy we have to keep in
mind
much of pure mathematics looks like
speculation
and yet it will have applications
someday
when our understanding of the universe
improves if we had
uh the same attitude of not funding pure
mathematics
then what would have happened to
ramanujan
ramanujan was into pure mathematics
for a hundred years almost
his equations had no applications
in the real world
but today some of the the
math that he came up with
is finding applications in string theory
etc now even string theory is supposedly
a failed theory it has produced no real
world applications or predictions
but maybe someday it will
if you talk about matrix theory matrices
before the 1920s there was almost no
application of matrix theory
until mr heisenberg
needed that
for
matrix mechanics which is
which is one of the ways of uh
which is which is part of quantum
mechanics
and eventually matrices now today are
used everywhere of computers in
everywhere because
uh it's it has it is integral to
computer science and many other things
so the thing is this
mathematics describes
the patterns and regularities of the
universe itself
mathematics is always
at least a century ahead typically of
physics
if you stop funding mathematics
in the future physics won't progress
so that's why i agree that much of the
matter is done is just
being done
for the sake of publication publish or
perish much of it has no value and if
you look at the physics papers that are
being published today 95 of them are
just
i mean they don't really have any value
right they're not advancing the field of
physics further
look at the papers that are being
published from indian universities
especially in nuclear physics
mind-bogglingly dull
and
it really doesn't advance the field at
all in any way whatsoever and yet they
keep on publishing it that is the
academic system that we are in right now
that is the academic system across the
world publish or perish
the only
measure of
of an academician or scientist's
worth is how many papers he or she has
published in the past year in the past
five years and past 10 years that's all
it doesn't
matter if the papers are worth nothing
so it is the system that is forcing
scientists to do this
i can guarantee you
most of the scientists the really good
ones would prefer to publish one paper
in two or three years but a quality
paper
but they are forced to publish multiple
papers every year so they just come up
with whatever they can
so i would say that mathematics pure
mathematics is extremely important it is
vital to the future of physics
even though let's say 95 of it
is not really useful
some of it is
and it is for that small percentage of
of gold that we find in it that we
should fund the 100 of pure mathematics
it's an investment in the future
so i disagree that pure mathematics
should not be funded i think it is very
important i agree
that 95 or more of it is
not really useful
but yet it is important that we fund
science and fund pure mathematics too
okay we you once this is by vishal you
once once stressed the importance of
india developing relations with similar
like-minded non-english speaking
countries
can you please elaborate why it is
necessary and
how it would be achieved well
why is it necessary because the
world is run by the anglo-saxon empire
which is headquartered in washington
which and it has its offshoots outposts
all across the world
there are five major countries
us canada uk
australia and new zealand
and the headquarters is the u.s
the other countries are like wasall
states or colonies and there are a whole
bunch of other countries which are under
the control of this empire
it's called a superpower but it's
actually an empire it has all the
characteristics of the empire of an
empire the u.s empire is
inspired by
and modeled on the roman empire have you
seen the american express credit cards
what is the logo on that a roman
centurion
so uh
and the the
the english speaking world the
anglo-sphere the anglo-saxon empire the
superpower whatever you call it does not
want india to rise
it doesn't want any country to rise
and it doesn't want to make the same
mistake with india which it made with
china
in the 1970s 80s and onwards
they aided and abated the rise of china
they will not make the same mistake
again with india so india
is being used as a counterbalance they
would like to use india as a
counterbalance to china but not they
would not like to see india rise too
much beyond a certain point
and we in india would like india to rise
to its fullest potential and we know
what india's potential is because we
know history
the people who watch this channel know
history therefore
india will need to cooperate with
like-minded countries that are not part
of the hegemonic
force or empire that rules the world
that's why india has good relations with
countries like france with countries
like russia
and various other countries
so that's what india needs to do
cooperate with countries that don't mind
to see india don't mind don't mind
seeing india rise to its full potential
the french don't mind that well
that's as far as we know
so it's all about mutual cooperation
mutual benefit helping each other and
rising together
so that's why it's necessary and how can
it be achieved well by cooperating like
we cooperate with the russians with the
chinese or with the chinese sorry with
the french
and so on
so france the france india relationship
is an excellent example of how this can
be achieved
india and france have essentially a
strategic partnership
we are partnering in
defense manufacturing we are partnering
in the indian ocean region we are
partnering diplomatically even when
india and france are on opposite sides
kind of like when it comes to the russia
ukraine situation we don't criticize
each other like the americans are
constantly criticizing india
so that sort of mutually respectful and
beneficial relationship is what india
should try to achieve with lots of other
countries so that is an example of how
we can achieve it
okay
let's take another question
so shirot says there are many
similarities between greek and indian
mythology so is there a possibility that
the atlantis described by plato
is related to dwarka both submerged of
course good question interesting
question
so uh plato the greek historian writer
whatever
he spoke he wrote about this uh
legendary
city state of atlantis
it is supposedly it was supposedly uh an
island kind of thing
uh
built in uh concentric circles and there
was some kind of cataclysmic event
that caused this
island
to sink under the ocean and get
submerged and it was lost forever so
that's the story that plato tells us
and
historians archaeologists have been
looking for it everywhere
much of the uh
searching for atlantis was done in the
atlantic ocean and they even named the
ocean
after atlantis the atlantic ocean
but no such place has ever been found i
think
there is certainly a possibility
that he may have been referring to
dwarka but
event happened way before the time of
plato
the dwarka event the submergence of the
city of dwarka seems to have happened at
least 8 000
years before today if not even before
that
so um
maybe
that is the story he was trying to tell
with
a greek kind of name atlantis it is
possible but we still don't have uh
clinching evidence for for what it was
so as of today it's just a story we
don't have any evidence but it is quite
posi it is certainly possible to some
extent that he may have been referring
to the
indian city of dwarka possibly
because it's the only city
that we know of
um probably in the whole world
that has
submerged in the same way as plato
described atlantis being submerged in
the under the ocean so yeah possible
meenakshi srivastava says it is said
that when the asteroid hit the earth in
the jurassic period
a lot of volcanoes erupted in the indian
continent
where did these volcanoes go
interesting question
let us
go to the map
once again let me put the map up so that
i can explain what this is all about
here's the map come on here it is okay
so there is this region in india called
the deccan traps
it is madhya pradesh maharashtra central
india and so on
it is the so-called bad lands of india
mountainous hilly region
uh and it is a place where you had a
huge amount of volcanism
many many millions of years ago to be
more specific between 70 and 65 million
years ago enormous volcanism in this
region
so that is the dick and traps it's
called the deccan traps now
about seven between 70 and 65 million
years before today india was not where
it is today it was actually
uh
over here
so there is in in this region
in this overall region so india and
madagascar were both attached to the
continent of africa and because of plate
tectonics
the two regions detached the two land
masses detached from africa and india
went all the way and slammed into
eurasia which caused the formation of
the himalayas but 66 million years ago
india was somewhere over here
east of madagascar over what is called
the reunion hot spot
which is a volcanic region
so it is because of the volcanic
activity in that region that we had this
volcanism in india
and it kind of coincides with the
cretaceous paleogene extinction event
the chichalub
impact event the impact is known to have
happened in the yucatan peninsula of
mexico
and it is now believed that the
extinction of the non-avian dinosaurs
was caused by
um
by the cumulative effect of two two
events the chick-fil-a impact event and
the deccan traps volcanism
and maybe maybe possibly
the impact event may have made the
volcanoes erupt
with more volume possibly that's a that
is something that could have happened
so the volcanoes
are now extinct
the actual volcanic
source is in the indian ocean in the
reno hotspot
and today all you find all you will see
in india is the
the lava formations of the deccan traps
which is all across central india so you
can google that
go to google images and google deck and
traps and you will see what it looks
like
how about i do that right now
let me share the screen and show you
what the dick and traps looks like
so we go to google search
icon traps
and this is what it looks like
so that's
um
the remains of the deck and traps
it is
it's no longer active as you can see
so you can google it and check it out
and see what it looks like
all right um
let's take a couple of questions and
i'll take some live chat questions as
well
shweta asks 20 seconds rapid fire
questions what do you prefer choose you
cannot say none
nice bank balance or nice holiday bank
balance because if you have bank balance
you can have undermining holidays
books that i would always prefer physics
but i don't mind both
love or respect both
affection or perfection affection
perfection is impossible
tango or ballroom dance tango santorini
or santorini santorini
chuching says what do you eat
in a day
i typically try to eat one meal in a day
all you can eat in one meal
so
i stay i prefer not to eat any wheat or
rice products no
carbohydrates of that kind cereals i get
my carbohydrates from vegetables lots of
vegetables and i try to
consume about 100 grams or so of protein
per day
so typically it's one meal a day
as much as i can eat huge meal but just
once uh once in a day and it it's not
always possible to do that when i'm
traveling when i go to when i'm
traveling and
staying in the hotel
or whatever then it's not possible to
always stick to that that discipline
so it's not a hard and fast rule but i
try to do that as much as possible
uh the first four months of this year i
was completely i was able to stick to
that
uh
without a single break the past couple
of months i've been traveling a bit and
also it's not been quite that
disciplined but that's typically the
kind of routine i have one meal a day
lots of vegetables and about 100 grams
of protein from various protein sources
that's what i eat in a day
okay let's take some live chat questions
um
mountainside says what are your thoughts
on mount kailash being a pyramid with
immense energy prove it
when you say when you say pyramid you
mean something that is that has been
built by humans or maybe by aliens
listen what energy so there is no proof
of what these claims that people make
it's a pyramid with some nuclear reactor
inside aliens have built it in this
immense what kind of some kind of energy
there there is absolutely no evidence
for that
so
unless somebody can provide evidence for
this i don't i will not take it
seriously obviously not
have you ever punched anyone
not in recent times not in the past
long time
but yeah when your kids you you
indulge in some hanky-panky some rough
play yeah
especially when you are a boy so yeah as
kids you do all that but yeah not not
in in recent times i i
i have never been an aggressive person i
am not a violent person i love peace
i love non-violence
so i am not somebody who is
prone to punching people
unless well i have no option
yeah
what's my view on you all harares
sapiens i have the book i've had it for
three four five i don't know how many
years i've never read it unfortunately
so i don't know
i don't know people seem to have a very
high regard and opinion about this book
i don't know maybe someday i'll bring
myself around to reading it
um somehow i mean i've never quite felt
the urge to read it even though i have
it
like i say i buy books i
i buy more books than i can read and i
read and i've read more books than i've
bought so that's the situation where i'm
in i have a reading backlog that's about
that's more than 100 books long
so uh
this book is still something that i have
not yet
uh started reading or tried to read but
i have it
come on ask me some interesting question
come on guys and girls
they just says was sumeria another
civilization formed by the outward
migration of indians i would say no
sumerian culture is very different from
ancient indian culture obviously
sumerian culture is no longer
extinct today
but the culture they had was
polytheistic but it was very different
from indian culture so
from what i have read and studied i have
not been able to see any significant
connections
between indian culture and sumerian
culture it most likely is
[Music]
indicates that these are two separate
ethnic groups into separate cultures or
civilizations
so the answer is most likely
no
with increasing tension in the
asia-pacific region how do you see
india's position india's position is
very simple we look out for our own
national interest
and
things that of that happen far away if
they don't affect our national interest
they don't concern us
we will not interfere
in the matters of other countries and we
demand that nobody
interferes in our internal matters
so uh
so that is overall what india's position
is
if there is
some incident in the asia-pacific region
india will take appropriate measures if
it affects india's national interest and
typically today in the interconnected
world that we live in
something that happens 3000 kilometers
away will end up affecting you as well
so india will put its national interest
first if there is a chinese invasion of
taiwan we will take appropriate measures
to safeguard our national interest
if there is an incident between china
and the philippines china and vietnam
china and japan
the senkaku islands or whatever if there
is something like that that happens we
will take appropriate measures to
safeguard our national interest and
that's all it is
so that is going to be india's position
as of today as of now
okay um
what are my views about our external
office minister dr jayshankar and recent
statements made by him i have a video
about that look it up
uh
i think he is the best external affairs
minister we have probably ever had
so yeah i have a very very high regard
for dr jayshankar and
the way he is uh
navigating india
through the uh
geopolitical sphere very good very good
job
and
so yes i'm um i have a very high regard
for him and what he's doing
okay let's take some more questions
some more questions ask me something
interesting something i've not answered
before
india australia thais are getting
stronger
we are seeing india australia ties are
getting stronger what can we conclude
the u.s trying to strengthen the hold in
the region india australia ties are
essentially india u.s ties
so if india australia are getting
stronger it means
india u.s ties are getting stronger
australia is a u.s colony or
a u.s project or a u.s possession that's
what australia is
so yeah when india and australia are
doing well it means the india and the
u.s is also doing well
uh what are your views on the astra
missiles the astra missile is
an air-to-air missile
it is something that a fighter aircraft
would fire at another fighter
aircraft to take it out
so i
think that we are now inducting these
missiles the the
mark one version the v1 version
not the vehicle version sorry the mark
one version of this missile into our air
force into the uh
cages jets
the sukhoi's jaguars etc it's an
excellent missile
the mark one version seems to have if i
recall correctly a range of about
120 kilometers
and the mark ii version that is now
being
tested most likely soon
it will have a range of about 160
kilometers or so
yeah so these are excellent missiles
very good missiles they have performed
very well in all the tests and i can't
look forward i mean i'm i'm very happy
to see that we are inducting
more and more indigenous technology into
our armed forces so my views are that my
view is that these are excellent
world-class missiles and it's great that
we have this missile now so we don't
need to buy such missiles like the
meteor missile or whatever else
or the russian missiles from other
countries
great great development
okay let's take a couple of questions
if time is money why aren't we making a
time machine yeah good question i'll
think about it
um
how to develop the art of asking quality
questions
uh that's an interesting question how
how to ask quality questions
well
you should ask yourself what's the
purpose for you
of asking questions
is the question supposed to benefit you
is it supposed to benefit other people
so
a question needs to
be something that gives you new
information that helps you learn
something
and yeah that's that's what i i guess
i can say as long as the question
brings forth new knowledge
that you haven't acquired in the past
it's a good question
please have a sports podcast
well typically
uh for me it's history science and
geopolitics
i did one ipl pod
ipl live stream
in which i hardly looked at the qriket
so i don't know maybe i'll do it in the
future maybe
i i do like sports big fan of certain
sports so
yeah maybe i could do that in the past
in the future
right
is the african continent really
splitting into two pieces
uh i have not seen any evidence of that
there is the rift valley of course where
there is this
two tectonic plates that have uh split
apart
and maybe that's how
our ancestors split off from the other
species like the chimpanzees in the
gorillas possibly
but no there is no evidence that the
african continent is splitting into two
pieces
right uh
who was sher shah sorry was he
no he was not liberal who he was not
tolerant he was an afghan born in bihar
he ruled over delhi for five years he
and
yeah there is no evidence that he was
liberal or tolerant or whatever that
some people claim
did he have any contribution towards
india what can you contribute if you
ruled for five years nothing nothing
much
i know some people won't like what i
said but
well
i'm not here to please everybody
um
when are you showing your entire
bookshelf
i will not show all my secrets
certain books are not to be shown
i'm just kidding maybe someday i'll do
it maybe
where was that
why are they not trying to bring back
the tasmanian tiger
you can't bring everything back
it's not possible i mean we're not gods
that we can just create any species back
back
or out of a few cells that you may have
found
some people are trying to recreate the
the extinct mammoth
we find mammoths all the time
but it's not really possible you know
i mean thus far it has not really
succeeded i'm sorry what is all this
i was trying to look for something which
has disappeared okay somebody asked uh
there's a
super chat question let's take this one
uh raul thank you uh i loved your
chingish khan video and your perspective
on how history is flawed
what do you think about the yasa laws
and do you see the relevance in today's
time
so the yasa laws were the laws of the
mongol empire the laws that were most
likely instituted by
shungish khan himself
these laws were never written down
but
what these laws were was known because
they were enforced and implemented
a whole bunch of do's and don'ts and
what you could do what you could not do
and what punishments were given for what
crimes so one of the things is that
women
were held in very high regard you could
not kidnap a woman you could not do what
uh you know abuse a woman in any way and
i think there was a death penalty for
that
and so on so forth so there was a whole
code of laws
that the mongols
followed and it was applied all across
the mongol empire the enormous mongol
empire
which essentially encompassed
approximately half of the known world
for the time
so the yasa laws where
are they relevant in today's times well
i think the punishments
that were
prescribed
in these laws may be seen as barbaric in
today's day and age
possibly i mean people would say what
about human rights what about democracy
and all that so maybe they are not
relevant today but they were very much
relevant for that time and there were
the laws were
implemented and enforced uniformly
across all subjects
whether you were a common soldier
whether you were male or female whether
you were mongol or non-mongol
whether you were royalty or not
everybody
was subject to these laws
so there was uniformity in the
application of the laws and when you
have that sort of discipline that's what
is the foundation of a really strong and
powerful empire
so that's what i can say in brief about
the aslos i think
on some websites there is a there are
lists of what the laws were like
so if
someone is interested they can look that
up so that's what i can say in brief
about the yasa laws
how much how long will it take for india
to become self-reliant in defense maybe
10 or 20 years maybe 20 years
uh
10 years is maybe too too short a time
for that
but most likely within 20 years we could
become more or less self-reliant in
defense
as long as we invest properly in the
in uh defense industry
and create a self-sustaining
industry and and ecosystem
and we bring in the private players
for creating and manufacturing spare
parts and various components of the
defense equipment so that is all
happening right now that's very much
happening now so i'm very confident that
in the next 20 years we would be
more or less self-reliant in
the defense
industry
and i think that's that's it for today i
know there are lots of other questions
but we are almost at the two hour mark
so i'm gonna stop it here thank you very
much all of you
for your questions
very interesting questions as always and
let's do it again
next week
until then take care
and see you next week thank you